Guide to the Gaston Liébert papers, 1866-1929
Liébert, Gaston papers, 1866-1929
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gaston Liébert papers, 1866-1929.
4435
Gaston Liébert.
3.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, clippings, letters, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters, documents, and photographs of Gaston Liébert, including official correspondence with Paris and Hanoi and personal correspondence from other French diplomats in China and Indochina. Material emphasizes problems in the Sino-Vietnamese border area during 1899-1900 and activities of Vietnamese revolutionaries in China, Macao, and Hong Kong before and during World War I. There are also documents relating tariff and debt negotiations with China after the Boxer Rebellion and to an British commercial treaty with China.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Gaston Ernest Liébert was born in Paris in 1866. He entered the Naval College in 1884 and served in the Navy for seven years. In 1893, he entered the diplomatic corps and was sent to the Far East in 1898. He served as French Vice-Consul to Pakhoi and Tunghing (China), 1899-1901; envoy for a special mission to the French Legation in Peking following the Boxer Rebellion, 1901-1902; French Consul to Hong Kong, 1903-1916; and Consul-General in New York, 1916
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, documents, and photographs of Gaston Liébert, including official correspondence with Paris and Hanoi and personal correspondence from other French diplomats in China and Indochina. Material emphasizes problems in the Sino-Vietnamese border area during 1899-1900 and activities of Vietnamese revolutionaries in China, Macao, and Hong Kong before and during World War I. There are also documents relating tariff and debt negotiations with China after the Boxer Rebellion and to an British commercial treaty with China.
Included is a large mss. map, 1900; copies of dispatches and political directives; personal papers from Liébert's career, from Naval School in 1887, to his naval duty, and to his diplomatic and foreign affairs responsibilities in various places; social and family correspondence from his years in New York; an album of copies of documents and photographs relating to Liébert family history and genealogy; a 1901 correspondence book; and photographs and a diary from his tenure in Peking.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Liébert, Gaston.; Cu´`o´ng Ð?ê.; Lu´o´ng, Ngoc Quy´ên.; Mai, Lão Bang.; Nguy^~en, Thiên Thuât.; Phan, Bôi Châu, 1867-1940.
Subjects:
Nationalism--Vietnam.; Diplomatic and consular service--China.; Diplomatic and consular service--United States.; Diplomats.; Consuls.
Places:
France--Foreign relations--China--20th century.; Diplomatic and consular service, French.; Vietnam--History--1858-1945.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--History--Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Pakhoi, 1899-1900
  - Information on the Pakhoi Region (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Local Political and Military Developments (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - French Strategic Concerns in the Region (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incidents of Piracy and Smuggling, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lung Mun Affair, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incidents of Piracy and Smuggling, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cases Involving Vietnamese on Chinese Territory (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dealings with Chinese Officials (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Catholic Missions and Missionary Affairs, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Missions and Missionary Affairs, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Matters Relating to Kwangchow Wan and Hainan (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Affairs (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press Clippings (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hong Kong, 1913-1914
  - General Correspondence, Jan. 1913-Apr. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, May 1913-Aug. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, July 1913-Sept. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence - French Consulate at Canton, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence - Govenor General's Office (Hanoi), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence - Other, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Arrest of Vietnamese with Bombs in Hong Kong, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Phan Boi Chau and Cuong De, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mai Lao Bang, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Press Clippings, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, Jan. 1913-Mar. 1914 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, Apr. 1913-June 1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, July 1914-Sept. 1914 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, Oct. 1914-Dec. 1914 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence - French Consulate at Canton, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Personal Correspondence - Govenor General's Office (Hanoi), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence - Other, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Press Clippings, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Information on Suspected German Plots, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cuong De, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arrest of Phan Boi Chau and Mai Lao Bang, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arrest of Nguyen Ba Trac (Cu Trac), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arrest of Luong Ngoc Quyen (Luong Lap Nham), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, Jan. 1915-Mar. 1915 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, Apr. 1915-June 1915 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, July 1915-Sept. 1915 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, Oct. 1915-Jan. 1916 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence - French Consulate at Canton, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence - Govenor General's Office (Hanoi), 1915 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence - Other, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Press Clippings, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Hong Kong, 1915-1916
  - Information on Suspected German Plots, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Phan Boi Chau, 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cuong De, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Arrest of Hoang Trong Mau and Le Duc Nhuan, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Arrest of Nguyen Thien Thuong (Hai Thac), 1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Agents and Informers - General (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Agents and Informers - Kuan Yan Fu (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Agents and Informers - "B.N." (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chinese International Affairs, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chinese International Affairs, 1914-1916 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence in Chinese (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photographs and Name Cards (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Liebert's Departure, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Liebert
  - Liebert - Navy, 1884-1889 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Liebert - Navy, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Liebert - Navy, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Liebert - Navy, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Liebert - Navy, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Liebert - Diplomatic, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Liebert - Diplomatic, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Liebert - Diplomatic, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Liebert - Diplomatic, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Liebert - Diplomatic, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Liebert, 1866-1869 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Liebert, 1879-1889 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Liebert, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1897-1898 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 2-10)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 11-14)
  - Liebert - Correspondence, 1901-1902 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Question du Whangpou Amelioration du Pei-ho, 1901 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Revision du tarif chinois et negotiations commercials, 1901-1902 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Rarriff Revision, 1901-1902 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dette chinoise, 1901-1902 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - British Commercial Treaty with China, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Notes sur Traie de commerce anglo-chinois, Sept. 1902 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - New York Herold - Champagne (ship), 1898 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations for Legion of Honor, 1901-1905 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Legion d'Honneur, 1912 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Trask, Katrina (Yaddo), 1917 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Telegrams, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1918-Jan. 1919 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Legion d'Honneur, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Feb. 1919-Aug. 1919 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Congradulations for Legion of Honor, Sept. 1919-Oct. 1919 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Sept. 1919-Dec. 1919 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Congradulations, vita, etc., 1919-1920 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Courrier des Etats-Unis, May 15, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - New York and Havana, 1916-1923 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Numbered Letters, 1916-1923 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1929 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Appointment as Ministre Plenipotentaire a New York, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Notes on Astrological (?) Consultations (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Notes sur les origines des populations de l'Europe occidentales (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Notes on Georges de Farensbach (Box 12, Folder 28)
- Documents
  - Certificate of Confirmation, 1877 (Box 8)
  - Diploma - Bachelier es Sciences, 1884 (Box 8)
  - Broadside - Bal du Mardi Gras, 1886 (Box 8)
  - Passports to Constantinople and St. Petersburg, 1894; 1897 (Box 8)
  - Safe Conduct decree - St. Petersburg, 1894 (Box 8)
  - Calling cards, ca. 1917 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Visiting cards, portraits (Box 9)
  - Album - portraits and medallions (Box 10)